# Maria L. DiGiano PhD

551 Dawn Dr. Sunnyvale, CA 94087 (352) 328-9688 mdigiano@gmail.com

Environmental anthropologist with extensive experience in addressing conservation and development challenges through research and practice in the developing world, specifically focusing on land tenure, community-based natural resource management and climate change. Experienced in research design, qualitative and quantitative methods and project management. Exceptional writing, communication and organizational skills, with the ability to work with people across academic disciplines and engage stakeholders within diverse cultural settings.

#### **RELEVANT EXPERIENCE**

#### Research Consultant, Earth Innovation Institute, January 2014- present

- Collaborate with Sustainable Tropics Alliance, a consortium of NGOs in the global south, in developing models for Low Emission Rural Development. Specifically, contribute to a cross-regional synthesis of progress towards Low Emission Rural Development in Brazil, Mexico, Peru, Indonesia and Kenya.
- Contribute to a report on contractual farming arrangements with smallholders in Brazil, Ecuador and Colombia contracted by the ProForest Initiative.

### Research Consultant, Stanford University, February 2014- present

- Develop a research project to examine the impacts of children's participation in field science programs at NatureBridge, an environmental education program, within the National Parks System.
- Disseminate findings to practitioner audiences as well as in peer-reviewed publications.

## Land Tenure Consultant, UN-Habitat Global Land Tool Network, May-July 2014

Prepared a review of Mexico's communal property regime (ejidos), using field research based case studies as well
as synthesis of literature.

### Postdoctoral Research Associate, Stanford University, May 2012- June 2013

- Led a research project in conjunction with Dr. Nicole Ardoin (Stanford University's Woods Institute for the Environment/Graduate School of Eduction) to design and pilot innovative evaluation tools for field-based science education programs.
- Coordinated with multiple stakeholders in research design and implementation, including partners within NatureBridge (field-based science program), academics, primary school teachers and students.

## PhD Student, University of Florida, January 2006-May 2011

 Designed, implemented, managed and evaluated research projects on conservation and development issues in Latin America, including land tenure policy reform in Mexico, land tenure and community forestry in Mexico and Guatemala, and community responses to natural disaster in Mexico. Research findings were published in peerreviewed journals.

#### MS Student, University of Florida, August 2003-December 2005

Conducted research on a payments for environmental service program in the Brazilian Amazon in collaboration
with a local NGO, the results of which were presented to numerous stakeholders in Brazil, including the Governor
of Acre, policy makers, rural extension agents, and communities, to facilitate dialogue as to the potential impacts
on forests and livelihoods.

# Agricultural Extension Agent, United States Peace Corps, Paraguay, September 1998-February 2002

- Designed, implemented and managed community-based projects to address and promote soil conservation, local
  capacity building, market gardens, and family nutrition.
- Developed and facilitated training sessions for Peace Corps volunteers and their Paraguayan counterparts.

### **EDUCATION**

## University of Florida, Ph.D., Interdisciplinary Ecology/ Anthropology, 2011

Areas of research: Land tenure, common property regimes, environmental anthropology, tropical conservation and development, community forestry, political ecology

Dissertation: Privatizing the Commons? A Political Ecology of Mexico's 1992 Agrarian Reform, Quintana Roo, Yucatan Peninsula

University of Florida, M.S., Interdisciplinary Ecology, 2006

*Areas of research*: Payments for environmental services, livelihoods, deforestation, environmental policy *Thesis*: Assessing the potential impacts of payments for environmental services on household income and land use among extractivists and colonists in Brazil's western Amazon

University of North Carolina, B.A., US History, 1996

### **RELEVANT PUBLICATIONS**

Nepstad, D., D. McGrath, C. Stickler, A. Alencar, A. Azevedo, B. Swette, T. Bezerra, M. DiGiano, J. SHimada, R. Seroa da Motta, E. Armijo, L. Castello, P. Brando, M. Hansen, M. McGrath-Horn, O. Carvalho, L. Hess (2014). Slowing Amazon deforestation through public policy and interventions in beef and soy supply chains. *Science*.

DiGiano, M. (2014) "The push to privatise: Mexico's 1992 reforms and impacts on forest ejidos" Contributing author to the following book chapter: Ellis, E.A., K.A. Kainer, J.A. Sierra Huelsz and P. Negreros-Castillo. In Press. Community-based forest management in Quintana Roo, Mexico. Chapter In: Cashore, B., W. de Jong, G. Galloway, P. Katila and P. Pacheco (eds.). Forests under pressure: local responses to global issues. IUFRO (International Union of Forest Research Organizations) World Series, Vol. xx. IUFRO, Vienna.

DiGiano, M., E. Ellis, and E. Keys (2013). Changing Landscapes for Forest Commons: Linking land tenure and forest cover change following Mexico's 1992 Agrarian Reform. *Human Ecology* 41 (5), 707-723.

DiGiano, M. (2013). Anthony Hall: Forests and Climate Change: The Social Dimensions of REDD in Latin America. *Human Ecology*, 1-3.

Romero, C., S. Athayde, J.E. Collomb, M. DiGiano, M. Schmink, S. Schramski and L. Seales. (2012). Conservation and Development in Latin America and Southern Africa: Setting the Stage. Ecology and Society 17 (2): 17. [online] URL: http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol17/iss2/art17/.

DiGiano, M., A. Racelis (2012). Robustness, Adaptation and Innovation: Forest communities in the wake of Hurricane Dean. *Applied Geography* 33, 151-158.

Barismantov, J., A. Racelis, K. Biedenweig and M. DiGiano (2011). When Collective Action and Tenure Allocations Collide: Outcomes from Community Forests in Quintana Roo, Mexico and Petén, Guatemala, *Land Use Policy 28*, 343-352.

J. Barismantov, A. Racelis, G. Barnes and M. DiGiano (2010). Tenure, Timber and Tourism in Quintana Roo, Mexico. *International Journal of the Commons* 4(1), 293-318.

Kainer, K., M. DiGiano, A. Duchelle, L. Wadt, E. Bruna, J. Dain (2009). Partnering for greater success: Local stakeholders and research in tropical biology and conservation. *Biotropica* 41(5), 555-562.

DiGiano, M., A. Racelis, G. Barnes and J. Barsimantov (2008). The Varying Effects of Neoliberal Land Policy on Communal Property in Mexico. *Proceedings of the Meeting of the International Association of the Study of the Commons*, Cheltenham, UK, July 14-18.

Stickler, C., W. Bartles, M. DiGiano, R. Veluci, K. Keefe, and W. Hart (2004). An evaluation of International Finance Corporation financing of Grupo André Maggi in the soybean sector: Environmental and social impact considerations, Published online at Amazonia.org- http://www.amazonia.org.br.

### **LANGUAGE SKILLS**

Spanish (advanced), Portuguese (intermediate), Yucatec Maya (beginner), Guaraní (intermediate)